Ninety-nine percent of us have the dream of listeners.
99 %مننا لده الحلم بأن يكون من بين المستمعين.
Not being the musicians -- the listeners, right?
لا أقول العازفين -- بل المستمعين, أليس صحيحا؟
And we crave one thing,
و نشتاق لشئ واحد
even though we kind of don't know it all the time.
حتو و لو منا نوعا ما لا نعرف فى أى وقت تحديدا.
We crave to be in the room with the musician
نشتاق لنكون فى نفس القاعة مع العازفين
the day it was recorded, the day it was played.
يوم أن سجلت و عزفت مقطوعاتهم.
And we go to live concerts, and we get that as much as we can.
و نحن نذهب إلى حفلات موسيقية حية, بالقدر الذى نستطيعه.
But then we listen to the other 99 percent of our stuff recorded.
لكن نستمع إلى 99 % لتسجيلاتنا.
And it turns out the further back you go in history,
و يتبين أنه كلما رجعنا إلى الماضى ,
the little rougher it sounds.
تزداد الضوضاء المصاحبة للموسيقى.
And so we said, there's a solution to this.
لذلك قلنا , هناك حلا لتلك المشكلة.
Let's separate the performance, as a thing,
دعونا نتعامل مع الآداء كشئ منفصل
out from the recording, which was how it was made.
عن التسجيل, و الذى صنع التسجيل أصلا بواسطته.
You know, the thing with microphones in the room and all that day.
كما تعلمون, المايكروفونات فى تلك القاعة كوال ذلك اليوم.
But the performance itself was how the musicians worked their fingers,
و لكن الآداء نفسه هو الكيفية التى قام بها العازفين بتحريك اصابعهم,
and what instruments they were using.
و ما الآلات التى إستخدموها.
And it's the data hidden inside the recording.
و هى البيانات الخفية داخل التسجيلات.
In order to do this, it's a lot of hardware and software
و لكى نقوم بذلك, كان هنك الكثير من العمل الفعلى و العمل بواسطة برامج الكومبيوتر
that runs in a very high resolution.
و الذى يدار بمستوى فائق جدا.
And Yamaha makes an incredible thing called the Disklavier Pro
و قامت شركة ياماها بصناعة ذلك الشئ الهائل المسمى ديسكلافيار برو,
that looks like a nice grand piano there.
و الذى يبدو لنا كبيانو كبير هنا--
And you probably didn't realize it's going to do all these things --
و من المحتما أنكم لم تلاحظوا أنه هو الذى سيقوم بكل تلك الأشياء--
but full of solenoids, and fiber optics, and computers
و هو ملئ بالملفات اللولبية و الألياف الضوئية, و أجهزة الكومبيوتر
and all this kind of stuff. The highest resolution out of Japan.
و كل تلك الأشياء-- و هى أعلى تقنيات من اليابان.
And this just didn't work until we could cross this line that says high-definition.
و هذا الأمر لم ننجح فى القيام به إلا بعبورنا إلى عصر الـ هاى ديفينشن = المواصفات القياسية الفائقة
And we were able to cross this line, called the uncanny valley,
و كان بمقدورنا العبور لهذا العصر, والذى يسمى بوادى العجائب
in terms of -- artificial intelligence terms.
و فقا لمصطلحات الذكاء الإصطناعي.
We have a process where we, you know,
لدينا عملية حيث
kind of put it into the computer and digitize it, and then a whole lot of analysis.
نقوم بوضع المقطوعة داخل الكومبيوتر و نحولها لصيغة رقمية ثم الكثير من عمليات التحليل
And we look at every single note,
و نفحص كل نوتة,
and all the attributes of those notes:
و كل الخصائص لتلك النوتات:
how hard they were struck, and how they were held down,
بأى قدر من القوة تم النقر و كيفية الإستغراق أثناء الضغط,
and how you move the fingers.
و كيف تحرك أصابعك.
So we had to develop a whole new science of how you move your fingers.
لذلك قمنا بإبتكار علم جديد خاص بالكيفية التى نحرك بها أصابعنا.
And, you know, it's a thing your piano teacher teaches you,
و هو ما يقوم مدرس البيانو بتعليمه لك,
but we never had a science behind these kinds of things.
و لككنا لم نحظى يوما بمنهج علمي منظم وراء تلك العملية.
I'm going to start with Glenn Gould.
سأبدا معكم بـ جلين جولد.
He died 25 years ago this year, and was born 75 years ago this year.
مات من 25 سنة (1982), و ولد منذ 75 عاما.(1932)
Was a beloved pianist, maybe the great cult pianist of the twentieth century.
كان عازف بيانو محبوب , ربما معشوق الجماهير الأول فى القرن الـ 20.
He just got tired of being in front of an audience,
أصابه الإرهاق من العزف الحي,
and felt like -- a performing monkey was, in fact, his term.
و شعر كأنه " القرد المؤدى" فى الواقع كان هذا هو تعبيره.
So he stepped back, and did nothing but the crafting of his work.
و من ثم إعتزل ذلك, و لم يقم بشئ سوى كتابة الأعمال.
And Gould's specialty was playing Bach.
و مان جولد متخصص فى عزف أعمال باخ.
His maybe most famous recording
و هى تكاد تكون أشهر تسجيلاته
was something called "The Goldberg Variations."
أسم المقطوعة " تنويعات جولدبيرج"
Bach only wrote themes and variations one time.
كتب باخ تيمات و تنويعات فى بداياته.
He wrote some early pieces,
كتب عدة تنويعات كانوا باكورته,
but late in his life, in his mature period,
و لكن فى مرحلة نضجه لاحقا
he said, "Here's a theme -- 30 variations."
قال, " هاكم تيمة و 30 تنويعة"
In fact, the theme isn't even the melody, it's the bass line.
فى الواقع التيمة ليستى هى اللحن , و لكنها الخط القاعدي.
And Gould recorded it in two major recordings that you may know about,
و سجل جولد تسجيلين أساسيين ربنا أنكم على دراية بهما,
one in mono, and one in stereo.
و احدا أحادي (مونو) و الآخر مجسم (ستريو).
And the one in mono, by the way, he used the pedal,
و الأحادى -بالمناسبة- يستخدم فيه دواسة البيانو,
and as he got older, he said, "No, no, wait a minute.
و عندما تقدم فى العمر قال , " لا لا , إنتظروا دقيقة.
I'm going to get very scientific about this, and not use the pedal."
ٍاتعامل مع الأمر من وجهة نظر علمية و لن أستخدم الدواسة."
What I'd like you to hear live is the 1955 version,
و الذى أحبكم أن تستمعوا له هى النسخة الحية لـ1955.
and we'll play the first couple pieces of it.
و سنستمع إلى أول مقطوعتين منهما.
Glenn Gould, 1955.
جلين جولد 1955.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
How about that?
ما رأيكم فى هذا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So let me tell you a little bit how this was done.
دعونى أخبركم قليلا عن كيفية قيامنا بذلك.
First of all, let me get you to the end step.
فى البداية دعونى أخبركم عن الخطوة النهائية.
This is -- we have a fairly complex process
هذه -- لدينا إلى حدا ما عملية معقدة
that, you know, software and musicians and so on,
و هى , برامج كومبيوتر و موسيقيين و هلم جرا,
but when we're all done, we know that the ear is the final arbiter.
و لكن عندما إنتهى كلا منا, أدركنا أن الأذن هى الحكم الفيصل.
We can play the original in one ear, and a new recording in the other.
يمكننا عزف التسجيل الأصلى فى أذن , و التسجيل الحديث فى الأذن الأخرى.
So I'm going to do this for you right now, what you just heard.
لذلك سأقوم بعمل ذلك معكم الآن, الذى سمعتموه للتو.
And in the right speaker is going to be the original recording,
و السماعة على اليمين ستكون التسجيل الأصلي
and the left speaker is going to be the new recording,
و التى على الشمال ستكون التسجيل الجديد--
actually of an instrument just like that one,
فى الواقع آلة موسيقية كتلك,
and I'm going to play them together at the same time.
و ساقوم بعزفهم معا فى نفس التوقيت.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
That's the original. [Unclear] That's the two together.
هذه هى الأصلية.
Before "Jurassic Park,"
قبل فيلم حديقة الديناصورات,
there was no science for how skin hung off of muscle, right?
لم يكن هناك منهجا علميا لمعرفة كيف ينفصل الجلد عن العضلة, أليس كذلك؟
So, in the video world,
لذلك فى عالم الفيديو,
we've been able to invent, in our lifetimes, natural behavior.
كان فى وسعنا أن نخترع, و نحن على قيد الحياة, سلوكا طبيعيا.
And this is kind of another example
و هذا مثالا من نوع آخر
of putting a science behind natural behavior.
أن نضع السلوك فى منهج علمي
And then you heard the original.
و ها أنتم سمعتم التسجيل الأصلي.
Ultimately, I started with the experience.
فى النهاية, بدأت من خلال الخبرة.
And the experience is: I want to be in the room and hear the musicians.
و خبرتى هى: أريد أن أكون فى القاعة و أستمع إلى الموسيقيين.
Lots of you can afford to buy one of these.
الكثير منكم يمكنه تحمل تكلفة شراء واحدة من تلك الآلات.
But, if not, there is now high-definition surround sound.
و لكن , إذا لم تستطيعوا, يوجد الآن صوت محيطي بقيساسات فائقة.
And I got to tell you, if you haven't heard high-definition surround,
و لابد أن أخبركم, لو لم تستمعوا إلى صوت قياسي فائق الجودة و محيطي,
go down to your audio dealer, your audiophile dealer.
إذهبوا إلى لتاجر المعدات الصوتية
It's so involving compared to regular stereo.
هناك فارق كبير بينه و بين الصوت المجسم العادى (ستيريو).
But if you don't have that, maybe you can listen on your headphones.
و لكن لو لم تتمكن أيضا , ربما تستطيع الإستماع عبر سماعات الأذن.
And so on the same disk we have five recordings --
و هكذا لدينا خمس تسجيلات على نفس المكتب--
Sony has five recordings.
شركة سونى لديها خمس تسجيلات.
And you could listen in headphones
و فى إمكانك نن تستمع عبر سماعات الأذن
with this thing called binaural recording.
بذلك الشئ المسمى التسجيل زجي السماعات.
And it's a dummy head that sits in front of the instrument,
و هى رأس غبية التى تجلس قبالة آلة موسيقية,
and it's got microphones where the ears are.
و لديها سماعات حيث تتواجد الآذان
And when you put on headphones, and you listen to this,
و عندما تضع سماعت أذنك وتستمع إلى ذلك,
you're inside of Glenn Gould's body.
تصبح فى جسد جلين جولد.
And it is a chuckle until, you know, the musicians,
و هى ضحكة حالما --كما تعلم, الموسيقيون,
who are musicians who play the piano, listen to this, say,
عازفى البيانو, إستمع لهذه,
"I can't believe it! It's just what it's like to play the piano."
" لا أستطيع أن أصدق! شعورى و كأنى أعزف البيانو."
Except now you're inside Glenn Gould's body playing the piano,
عدا أنك داخل جسد جلين جولد و تقوم بالعزف,
and it feels like your fingers are making the decisions
و تشعر و كأن أصابعك هى التى تتحرك من تلقاء نفسها
and moving through the whole process.
خلال عملية العزف كلها.
It's a game changer.
إنه تغيير فى اللعبة.
Here's now something we know in spectacular quality.
و هاكم شيئا نعرفه بجودة مذهلة.
The whole process is very sensitive to temperature and humidity.
العملية بأكملها شديدة الحساسية للرطوبة ودرجة الحراراة.
What you heard today was not perfect.
الذى سمعتموه اليوم لم يكن مثاليا.
It's an amalgam of wood, and cast iron, and felt,
إنه سبيكة من الخشب و المعدن و اللباد,
and steel strings, and all these,
و أوتار معدنية, و كل هذا,
and they're all amazingly sensitive to temperature and humidity.
و كل تلك الأشياء شديدة الحساسية للرطوبة و درجة الحرارة.
So when you go into the recording session,
لذلك عندما تذهب إلى جلسة التسجيل,
you get to stop after every piece and rebuild the piano if you need to.
فإنك تتوقف بعد كل مقطوعة لتعيد ضبط البيانة لو تطلب الأمر ذلك.
There's the whole action there, sitting, kind of, on the side,
العملية كلها قابعة هناك ..نوعا ما على الجانب
and the dummy head and our recording engineers
و الرأس الصماء و مهندسي التسجيل
standing around while we rebuild the piano.
يتحلقون بينما نعيد ضبط البيانو.
Without putting dates next to these things,
بدون وضع تواريخ بجوار تلك الأشياء,
step-by-step music will be turned into data,
خطوة بخطوة, تتحول الموسيقى لبيانات,
like every field that's occurred in the past 35 or 40 years.
كأى مجال برز خلال الـ35 و الـ40 سنة الماضية.
Audio has come very late to this game --
الصوتيات جاءت متأخرة جدا على تلك اللعبة
I'm not talking about digitizing, and bits, and re-mastering.
لا أتحدث هنا عن الأرقمة, و القياس بالبايت , و تصنيع نسخ أكثر تفوقا--
I'm talking about turn it into the data that it was made from,
أنا أتكلم عن تحويلها إلى البيانات التى صنعت منها فى الأساس,
which is how it was performed.
و التى أديت من خلالها.
And audio came very late because our ears are so hard to fool --
الصوتيات جاءت متأخرة لأنه من العسير خداع آذاننا--
they're high-resolution, and they're wired straight to our emotions,
فالأذن شديدة الدقة, و مرتبطة مباشرة بعواطفنا,
and you can't trick them very easily.
و لا يمكنك خداعهم بسهولة.
Your eyes are pretty happy with some color and movement, you know.
عيناك تسعدان ببعض الألوان والحركة , كما تعلم.
All right, there's this episode of "Star Trek."
حسنا, يوجد هنا حلقة من مسلسل ستار تريك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I get it -- it was all just laid in for me yesterday there.
أنا أفهمها -- كل شئ فيها أصبح مفهوما بالنسبة لى بالأمس.
The episode of "Star Trek" for me was James Daly played Methuselah --
حلقة ستار تريك هى عندما قام جيمس دالى بعزف مقطوعة مَتُوشَالَحَ =ابو النبى موسى (ص)
remember this one?
أتتذكرونها؟
And at some point he's dancing with his --
و عند مرحلة معينة يقوم بالرقص عليها--
and I won't ruin the episode for you, from 1967.
و لن أحرق لكم الحلقة , التى عرضت فى عام 1967.
Right, do you know where I'm going?
حسنا, هل تعرفون إلى ماذا ارمى؟
And Nimoy, I'm sorry, Spock sits down at the piano,
و نيموى, اسف , سبوك يجلس إلى البيانو,
and he starts playing this Brahms waltz, and they all dance to it.
و يبدأ بعزف مقطوعة لرقصة الفالس لـ برامز, و الكل يرقص عليها.
And then Spock turns round, he goes,
و يستدير سبوك و يقول,
"James, I know all of the Brahms waltzes,
" جيمس, انا أعرف كل مقطوعات الفالس لـ برامز,
and I don't believe this is one of them in the category."
و أنا لا أعتقد أن تلك المقطوعة مصنفة كـ فالس."
That's where I'm at.
هذا ما كنت ارمى إليه.
I want to hear the waltzes Brahms didn't write.
أنا أريد ان أعزف مقطوعة للفالس لم يكتبها برامز أصلا.
I want to hear the pieces that Horowitz didn't play.
أريد ان أستمع لعزف لم يؤديه هوروفيتس.
But I believe we're on a path now, when we get to data,
و لكن أعتقد أننا فى الطريق لذلك عندما نحصل على البيانات
that we can distill styles, and templates, and formulas, and all these kinds of things,
فيمكننا من تحليل طرز العزف و قوالبه و تركيباته المختلفة و ما شابه--
again, that you've seen happen in the computer graphics world.
مجددا, الذى رايتموه فى عالم الكومبيوتر المصور
It's now coming in this world.
يصبح حقيقة فى هذا العالم.
The transition will be this one.
هذا الإنتقال سيكون الأتى.
It says right now, we think music is notes and how they're played.
يقال الآن , أننا نعتقد أن الموسيقى عبارة عن نوتات و الكيفية التى تعزف بها.
And I believe this is coming.
و أعتقد أن هذا سيأتى.
Because what you've just heard was a computer playing data --
لأان ما سمعتموه ليس إلا كومبيوتر يعزف بيانات--
no Glenn Gould in the room.
لا وجود لـ جلين جولد فى القاعة.
But yet, it was human.
و لمنه أيضا عزفا بشريا.
And I believe you'll get to the next step, the real dream of listeners.
و أعتقد أنكم ستمضون إلى الخطوة التالية, الحلم الحقيقى للمستمعين.
Every time you listen to a recording today,
فى كل مرة تستمع فيها إلى تسجيل موسيقي اليوم,
every time you take out your iPod and whatever,
فى كل مرة تأخذ فيها جهاز الـ آى بود خاصتك,
every time you listen to it, it's the same thing -- it's frozen.
فى كل مرة تستمع إليه, يقوم بعمل نفس الشئ-- طريقة عمل متجمدة.
Wouldn't it be cool if every time you listened, it could be different?
ألن يكون رائعا لو إستمعت فى كل مرة إليه و يفاجئك بشئ مختلف؟
This morning, you're sadder, you want to hear your song,
هذا الصباح انت حزين , تريد أن تستمع لاغنيتك,
the same song, played sadder than you did yesterday.
نفس الأغنية تؤدى لك بططريقة حزينة و مختلفة عن طريقة الأمس.
You want to hear it played by different musicians.
تريد أن يعزفها لك موسيقيون مختلفون
You want to hear it in different rooms and whatever.
تريد أن تستمع لها فى قاعات مختلفة و أيا ما يجول فى ذهنك.
We've seen all these "Star Treks," and they're all holodeck episodes as well.
رأينا كل حلقات مسلسل ستار تريك و و حلقاتهم الكارتونية أيضا.
Every time I listen to that, I get goose bumps.
كل مرة أستمع فيها لذلك , تنتابنى القشعريرة.
It's so amazing, it's so exciting.
إنه أمر مذهل و مثير.
Every time I listen to that recording it's like, "Oh my God,
كل مرة أستمع فيها لذلك التسجيل نتابنى حالة, ..يا إلهى,
I can't believe I'm in the same room. I can't believe this is happening."
لا أصدق أننى بنفس القاعة. لا أصدق أن هذا يحدث.
It's a way better experience
خبرة افضل بكثير
than whatever you're used to listening to, in whatever form.
من اية وسيلة إستخدمتها لتستمع من خلالها.
And lastly, I will wrap up with one minute of Art Tatum.
و أخيرا سوف أختتم بدقيقة مع تاتوم = عازف جاز أمريكى, أعمى. علم نفسه بنفسه.
So I've really overshot my budget here.
لذلك قد تخطيت ميزانيتى هنا.
We made a new recording of him
صنعنا تسجيلا جديدا له
playing in the Shrine Auditorium in September.
و هو يعزف قاعة شراين فى سبتمبر.
It was a concert he recorded in the Shrine Auditorium in 1949.
كان حفلا موسيقيا , سجل فى عام 1949 بقاعة شراين.
And I've got to tell you, we have this lab
و يجب أن أخبركم , أننا لدينا ذلك المختبر
where we build and measure everything, back in Raleigh, North Carolina,
حيث قمنا ببناء و قياس كل شئ فى رالى بولاية نورث كارولاينا,
and we flew out to Los Angeles.
و طرنا إلى لوس أنجيليس.
And as the president of the company,
و كرأيس للشركة,
I didn't feel real comfortable about where we were.
لم أشعر بالإرتياح عن المكان
That's a real uncomfortable feeling,
و هو شعور غير مريح بالمرة
when all the equipment's come out and a whole Sony team,
عندما جاءت كل المعدات و فريق شركة سونى
and people are going to be sitting there in the audience.
و الحضور على وشك الجلوس.
And we put the piano on the sweet spot of the stage in the Shrine,
و وضعنا البيانو على بقعة جميلة من خشبة المسرح--
which has not changed since 1949, still seats 6,000 people.
و الذى لم يتغير منذ عام 1949 , لا يوال يتسع لـ 6,000 مستمع--
And on the sweet spot on the stage, Tatum starts playing ...
و على البقعة الجميلة من خشبة المسرح , بدا تاتوم العزف...
and every note, every beat, every slur, every accent, every pedal
و كل نغمة , و إيقاع , و تداخل للنغمات مع كل تنويعة للصوت و ضغطات الدواسة
was perfect, because he played it for that room on that day.
كل ذلك كان مثاليا, لأنه قام بالعزف فى تلك القاعة فى ذلك اليوم
And we captured all that data all over again.
و سجلنا كل تلك البيانات مرة أخرى
And I want you to hear that right now.
و أريد منكم أن تستمعوا لتلك المقطوعة الآن.
And fortunately, it's right in here.
و لحسن الحظ فغنها هنا--
This is an encore he used to do.
هذه مقطوعة كان يطلب منه أن يكررها.
It's one minute long.
طولها دقيقة واحدة.
It's an Irish jig, and I want you to hear his humor.
رقصة جيج آيرلاندية, و أريد منكم أن تستمعوا لخفة ظله.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And that's just what the live audience did.
و هذا بالضبط ما فعله الحضور حينها.
So thank you very much, Michael, thank you for the opportunity.
حسنا , شكرا جزيلا, أشكرك على هذه الفرصة